Afternoon. We've
read your written submission on the Community Magistrates Legislation Amendment
Bill. We've got you down for 10 minutes.
Leave some time at the end if there's any questions from members. Over to you.
Sorry, Steven, we can't hear you.
Can you hear me okay now?
We can.
Sorry about that. My name is Steven Lack.
I'm presenting on behalf of the New Zealand Law Society together with my colleague,
Mr. Perry. And we say
that the Law Society would like to express its support for the
bill's objectives of improving timeliness in the District
Court.
Mm-hmm.
They're an important aim. It has significant potential benefits
for the community, for the justice system.
And access to justice in a timely manner is obviously a
significant issue that the Law Society places great importance in.
It's something which we place great prominence in, in many submissions before
this committee. So,
it is a noble objective, but there are a couple
of concerns that we would like to raise. And I'll address the first one.
Mr. Perry will address the latter two.
The first concern really in the bill, in the manner in which it's presently
drafted, is Clause 22.
That would,
if enacted, allow community magistrates to hear judge-alone
trials for Category 2 offenses carrying a maximum penalty of
up to three months imprisonment.
In the Law Society's view, that's a significant
expansion of the present role of community magistrates, and it's
not simply a minor step up, and
it's something that community magistrates, as a matter of standard,
are presently not or potentially not equipped to deal with.
Some of those cases can involve
complex and difficult evidential issues, factual
issues. Some examples of that are assault
offenses which occur in a family violence context.
There are offense provisions in the Misuse of Drugs Act.
For example, supply of Class C controlled drugs, which would
come within this provision. So they are the types of
offense that, generally speaking,
have difficult, complex, and potential
issues, a lot of interest to look out for, particularly in relation to
complainants and family violence matters and how that are dealt with in an
evidential context. So our concern primarily is
that these types of cases require careful and
consistent decision-making, and community
magistrates who don't necessarily have
a legal background, certainly it's not a requirement, and practicing lawyers are
prohibited from being community magistrates, may not be equipped
to properly deal with those types of cases.
So for that reason, the Law Society respectfully
recommends that community magistrates not be given the jurisdiction to preside over
those types of judge-alone trials.
And I'll pass it over to Mr. Perry.
Yeah. Thank you, Steven. And just one other point on Section
22, and it's really expanding what Steven's already
said. The risk is if community
magistrates have jurisdiction to hear
trials on Category 2 offenses, albeit at that cap of
three months imprisonment,
it may have the effect of potentially clogging up the
courts more than they already are.
The reason I say this is that
the first appeal court for decisions of a community
magistrate is the District Court.
The District Court, as it's currently constituted, is not well
set up to deal with appeals, as is the situation with
the High Court, which routinely hears appeals.
So in the event that an appeal is brought
against a decision of a community magistrate on a complex
evidential matter or whatever particular issue may arise in the context of
a hearing, that appeal is going to go to the District Court, and that's
going to tie up District Court judge time
dealing with that appeal. And as
the courts are currently scheduled, at least in the region where I practice,
there's not a good facility for that.
And I think the systemic risk is that community magistrates who aren't necessarily
legally qualified to deal with such complex
matters,
there may well be more appeals that flow
from decisions of community magistrates than would be the case for
a trial presided over by a District Court judge.
So
there's a real risk of slowing things down rather than speeding things up.
And I think for that reason,
as well as others, I think the committee should
give real consideration not to expanding that particular power of
community magistrates.
Now, the second concern that we want to highlight in our oral submissions
relates to the
ability of community magistrates to take pleas.
There are two--
Well, take pleas and enter convictions, I should say.
And these are separate but related issues.
So when it comes to taking a plea, that's a very
significant
point in the life cycle of a charge, and in
the context of a busy District Court,
it might be the case that pleas are entered in circumstances
where they perhaps ought not to be, particularly when we're
dealing with very high-level charges that could potentially carry life
imprisonment.
Our preference, as set out in the submission, is
that if community magistrates are to be empowered to take
pleas,
that
their ability to do so is capped at offenses punishable
by seven years imprisonment or less,
and thus excluding the high-level offenses
where questions of plea are going to have potentially very, very serious
consequences. Another matter that flows from the
entry of plea is Section 13 of
the Bail Act. So there are a number of provisions in the Bail Act which
restrict, in essence, the
ability of a defendant to get bail.
Where someone enters a plea, then
in essence, it becomes harder. And if a plea is entered before a community
magistrate, the question as to bail will inevitably come up,
and it may well be that community magistrates are not
well-equipped with their knowledge and their training to make an assessment
as to whether bail ought properly be granted.
The reason why that
presents a particular problem is that on the face of it, some charges that
may have potentially life imprisonment as a potential
sentencing outcome,
while a
defendant faces those charges, may nonetheless have good prospects of
getting bail for reason that they're very unlikely to get a
sentence of imprisonment. The classic example would be a low-level
supply charge for methamphetamine or a Class A drug,
notwithstanding the fact that it's like imprisonment by life.
If the quantities are low, then the normal sentencing outcome would be a
community-based sentence, and a community magistrate lacking legal
training
may not be well-equipped to make that assessment.
The other part of the submission relates to the entry of
convictions themselves. So a plea and a conviction are different
things. You can enter a plea and still not have a conviction entered
on the court record. Now, the entry of a conviction
has a lot of implications.
First,
if someone is ultimately to seek a discharge without conviction,
under Section 106 of the Sentencing Act,
if a
conviction is entered
when pleas are entered, then the ability of a defendant to make that
application is essentially
precluded. So we face a possible scenario where
a community magistrate might take a plea
into a conviction that they're not empowered to
sentence, and yet they're still having to make a
decision as to the entry of a plea,
which could well preclude a proper application
further down the track. So our position essentially is that
while community magistrates may be able to take pleas on matters that they
are
not equipped to sentence on,
or rather they're not permitted to sentence on, it would be preferable that they're
not able to enter convictions in those circumstances
for risk that
subsequent applications might be precluded.
Finally-
Steven, I might need to stop you there. I do have a question.
Mm-hmm.
We're very, very close to our time, if that's okay.
Unless you've got any closing remarks you might want to say.
No, that's fine.
Okay. Camilla Belich.
Thank you, and thanks for your helpful suggestions that we'll seek advice
on from officials. I just had a question around, we've had quite a few
submissions raise the issue of legal training for community
magistrates, and I know that you've raised that in terms of some of your
comments on
whether the changes are appropriate.
Do you have any comment to make generally on that aspect of it
as a factor? Or another aspect that we've received some
comment on is the duration of training that community
magistrates receive, which I think is about five days.
I don't know if you have any comment to make specifically on that, but thank you
for your other helpful suggestions.
I can briefly speak to that. I think there's a submission
made, I think, by the Law Association that
the
delimiting community magistrate jurisdiction based on the
level of the charge is not an appropriate proxy for the
complexity of a matter. Matters can be low level and yet very
complex. And the concern as to training
is
if community magistrates aren't legally qualified and they've only got five days
training, and I'm not privy to what their training is, then that creates real
concerns potentially for
the timeliness and effectiveness of the
judicial system. Simply put, we're all qualified
as lawyers appearing before the court.
Judges certainly are qualified. And it seems odd
that
someone could preside over a defended hearing with potentially complex
evidential matters and not be similarly qualified.
Thank you.
Okay. I'm sorry, Dan, I'm going to have to leave it there.
But thank you, Steven, and thank you, Steven, for joining us this afternoon.
Really appreciate your time and the submission as well.
Thank you very much.
Okay. I'll just ask members of the public to leave, and we'll just go into our
private consideration.
Yeah,
fine